Guide to the New-York Historical Society Board of Trustees Records 1939-1959 NYHS-RG 18
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society Board of Trustees records
1939-1959
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 18
4.5 Linear feet in 7 document boxes and 10 bound volumes (of unrestricted material)
In November 1937, a by-law change resulted in the creation of an independent Board of Trustees as the governing body of N-YHS. The New-York Historical Society Board of Trustee records (NYHS-RG 18) primarily includes the materials related to Board meetings, including agendas, minutes, committee reports, various documents distributed at the meetings, and some working files from 1939 forward. Records through 1959 are open for research; records after 1959 are currently restricted.
Accruals Note
Additional materials are expected to accrue to the record group although they will remain restricted for a time.
Arrangement Note
The record group is organized in several series that coincide with the executive administrations of N-YHS. Each series will be opened over time consistent with N-YHS's policy on access to Board and executive records. Only the first two series are currently open to researchers:
Series I. Board Minutes (1939-1958)
Series II. Official Papers (1939-1959)
Access Restrictions
N-YHS generally restricts the records of the Board of Trustees and the Executive Office for fifty years following the conclusion of the tenure of a President and CEO (formerly, Director). Accordingly, the record group is open through 1959, when Director R.W.G. Vail left N-YHS. The tenure of his successor, James Heslin, dated from 1960 to 1982, so those records are closed until 2033. Records from subsequent administrations will be opened in later decades.
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society Board of Trustee records (NYHS-RG 18) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1) include the minute books and official papers of the N-YHS governing bodies that existed prior to the creation of a Board of Trustees in 1937. The 1938 trustee minutes are also in that record group because they were bound with the 1937 minutes.
Scope and Contents Note
In November 1937, a by-law change resulted in the creation of an independent Board of Trustees as the governing body of N-YHS. The New-York Historical Society Board of Trustee records (NYHS-RG 18) primarily includes the materials related to Board meetings, including agendas, minutes, committee reports, various documents distributed at the meetings, and some working files from 1939 forward (the 1938 minutes are found in a different record group; see the Related Materials note). Records from after 1959 are currently restricted (see the Access Restrictions note).
New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Museums -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Letters (correspondence); Minute books.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Management.; New-York Historical Society. Board of Trustees
- Series I. Board Minutes, 1939-1958; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  Series I holds bound volumes of the minutes of trustee meetings from 1939 to 1958. These are the original minutes, signed by the Board Secretary, who was typically the Director. The minutes include information concerning acquisitions, dispositions, financial matters (e.g., investments, budgets), operations (e.g., policies, employee benefit plans), facilities, membership elections, publication initiatives, by-law changes, officer elections, programs (e.g., exhibitions, Strawberry Festivals, publicity), memorials, and consideration of loan requests.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in chronological order. Loose papers found inserted with the bound documents were removed and foldered in separate boxes; these are noted in the container list.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Although records through 1959 are open, the 1959 minutes are bound with the restricted 1960 minutes and so are restricted. The official papers for 1959 are open and hold much, perhaps all of the relevant content.
  - Board Minutes. January 17, 1939-December 17, 1940, 1939-1940 (Volume RG18.1)
  - Board Minutes. January 21, 1941-December 15, 1942, 1941-1942 (Volume RG18.2)
  - Board Minutes. January 19, 1943-December 19, 1944, 1943-1944 (Volume RG18.3)
  - Board Minutes. January 16, 1945-December 17, 1946, 1945-1946 (Volume RG18.4)
  - Board Minutes. January 21, 1947-December 22, 1948, 1947-1948 (Volume RG18.5)
  - Board Minutes. January 26, 1949-December 27, 1950, 1949-1950 (Volume RG18.6)
  - Board Minutes. January 24, 1951-December 17, 1952, 1951-1952 (Volume RG18.7)
  - Board Minutes. January 28, 1953-December 22, 1954, 1953-1954 (Volume RG18.8)
  - Board Minutes. January 26, 1955-December 26, 1956, 1955-1956 (Volume RG18.9)
  - Board Minutes. January 23, 1957-December 17, 1958, 1957-1958 (Volume RG18.10)
- Series II. Official Papers, 1939-1959; 3 Linear feet
  The Official Papers series includes the working files and packets of material related to the Board meetings through 1959. There is considerable overlap between the content of these files and the meeting minutes because much of the official papers includes the committee (library, museum, finance, etc.) reports that were replicated in the minutes. Nonetheless, the official papers do hold additional material of interest including budgeting worksheets, expense details, attendance sheets, staff notices, staff lists, and other matter. The official papers of the early 1940s hold some documents related to N-YHS's wartime precautionary measures. Membership application forms make up a sizable volume of the series.
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Includes a complete staff list as of 1939, including names, positions held, and date of hire; the document is particularly useful in illustrating the expansion of the staff in connection with the opening of the expanded building and programs.
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    Includes correspondence concerning N-YHS's consideration of generating its needed electricity through its own plant operation. Includes a calculation of the floor space in the Central Park West building.
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    Includes the draft report of the Board Committee in the Matter of the Preservation of the Aquarium Building in Battery Park; a detailed description "Resources of the Library" of N-YHS; the agenda for a meeting of art museum directors of December 20-21 in connection with wartime precautions, as well as other documents concerning World War II preparations; the "Rules and Duties of Attendants [e.g., guards, doormen, check room]"; program for the Stephen Collins Foster event, with manuscript of the printed content by George Zabriskie; and the certificate for an outstanding example of printing awarded to N-YHS by the New York Employing Printers Association for The Life of Emma Thursby.
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    Includes an assessment of the impact of the war on staffing and steps to be taken in response to the resource constraints.
  - Official Papers. Wartime Matters, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes correspondence, government directives, applications related to rationing, information about protecting N-YHS's skylights against air raids, savings bond program, secure storage options, and other matters. Also includes some other general facilities maintenance related documents, both for Central Park West and for the Thompson estate building on Long Island opened as a summer museum.
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Official Papers. Wartime Matters, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes documents concerning air raid fire protection and a military deferment.
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Official Papers (4 folders), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    Includes correspondence from other New York City institutions responding to N-YHS's survey of staff scheduling practices. Includes a report on the high school education programs currently presented and in development by N-YHS.
  - Official Papers (4 folders), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
  - Official Papers (2 of 6 folders), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Official Papers (4 of 6 folders), 1948 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    Includes a proposal for changes to manuscript accessions and access.
  - Official Papers (5 folders), 1949 (Box 4, Folder 5-9)
  - Official Papers (4 folders), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Official Papers (6 folders), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 5-10)
    Includes N-YHS's consideration of purchasing the 6-16 West 77th Street property.
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1952 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1953 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1954 (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1955 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1956 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1957 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Official Papers (2 folders), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - Official Papers (3 folders), 1959 (Box 7, Folder 9-11)
    Includes the new "Library Acquisition Policy" approved by the Board on May 27, 1959. Includes the remarks prepared by the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Association for four of the speakers at the opening of the exhibition at Federal Hall commemorating N-YHS's 155th anniversary.